Guide to the Charles S. Hastings Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Sheldon Hastings papers
1869-1930
MS 997
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
Correspondence, professional writings, and notes of Charles Hastings concerning research in and teaching of physics, astronomy, and optics at Johns Hopkins University and Yale University.
Hastings, Charles Sheldon, 1848-1932
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of estate of Charles S. Hastings, 1940.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers of Charles Sheldon Hastings consist of notebooks, lecture notes, letters, and other items relating to optics, astronomy, and physics. The letters are primarily from other scientists and deal with questions of optics and related matters. The largest group of letters is from William H. Goodyear of the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Science; they are accompanied by notes concerning architectural measurements of cathedrals made by Goodyear and Hastings. Other correspondents include Henry C. Lomb and his associates at the Bausch and Lomb Optical Company, with whom Hastings was consulting about a new microscope.
The bulk of the papers, made up of scientific writings, notebooks, and notes, some relating to Hastings' teaching at Johns Hopkins University and Yale University, is arranged in chronological order. There are, in addition, certificates of membership in the National Academy of Sciences of the United States and in the American Philosophical Society; a diary of a voyage taken by Hastings from Panama to Peru and of his arrival in the Caroline Islands; and an assortment of photographs taken in New Haven and Europe, many of them unidentified.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Hastings was born in Clinton, New York, on November 27, 1848. He received a Ph.B. from Yale in 1870, and a Ph.D in 1873. Between 1871 and 1873, he was instructor of physics at Yale, after which time he studied physics at the Universities of Heidelberg and Berlin and at the Sorbonne in Paris. From 1876 to 1884, he was associate professor of physics at Johns Hopkins University. He returned to Yale in 1884 to become professor of physics, a position he held until 1915 when he became professor emeritus. Hastings died in Greenwich, Connecticut, on January 31, 1932.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Sheldon Hastings, Ph.B. 1870.
Born November 27, 1848, in Clinton, N. Y.; Died January 31, 1932, in Greenwich, Conn.
Father, Panet Marshall Hastings (B.A. Hamilton 1838; M.D. Columbia 1842); physician in Clinton and Hartford; lecturer at Hamilton; connected with Hartford Hospital; son of Dr. Seth Hastings, Jr., and Huldah (Clark) Hastings, of Clinton. Mother, Jane (Sheldon) Hastings; daughter of Charles and Alicia (Lawrence) Sheldon, of Hartford.
Hartford Public High School. Engineering course; member The Colony and Berzelius.
Studied in Yale Graduate School 1870-73 (Ph.D. 1873); instructor in physics 1871-73; studied physics at Universities of Heidelberg and Berlin 1873-75 and at the Sorbonne, Paris, 1875-76; associate professor of physics at Johns Hopkins University 1876-1884; professor of physics at Yale from 1884 until retirement 1915, when made professor emeritus; co-author, with Professor Frederick E. Beach, '83 S.: Text Book on General Physics (1899) and Light, A Consideration of the More Familiar Phenomena of Optics (1901); author: New Methods in Geometrical Optics (1928); made an Officier de l'Instruction Publique at the Sorbonne 1889; corresponding member Societa degli Spectroscopisti Italiani; member National Academy of Sciences, American Association for the Advancement of Science, American Physical Society, American Philosophical Society (received Elliott Cresson Medal of the society 1926), and the United Church (Congregational), New Haven; president of Graduates Club Association 1905-07.
Married June 28, 1878, in Hartford, Elizabeth Tracy, daughter of Elisha Tracy and Catharine M. (Barker) Smith, and sister of Charles W. Smith, ex-'74 S. One daughter, Katharine Panet, ex-'04 Art, the wife of Horace W. Chittenden '03 S.
Death due to cerebral hermorrhage and arteriosclerosis. Buried in Cedar Hill Cemetery, Hartford. Survived by daughter.
Taken from Yale University Obituary Record, 1931-34, page 143.
Astronomy -- Observations; Optics; Physics; Science; Shipping; Asia; Physicists; Goodyear, W. H. (William Henry), 1846-1923; Hastings, Charles Sheldon, 1848-1932; Bausch & Lomb Optical Company; Johns Hopkins University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1879-1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - William H. Goodyear
      - Letters, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Notes, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bausch and Lomb Optical Company: letters and reports, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scientific papers
    - Astronomical observations, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Notebook: "Lectures on Optics-by Prof. Kirchhoff"; "Einleitung in die höhen Analysis von Prof. Königsberger"; "Notes on Apparatus", 1874, 1883-1884, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Notebook on optics and other scientific subjects, with notes on Europe, 1875, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notebook: "Experiments in the Application of Mathematics to Physical Problems, Given First Term in Winter 77-8 at the Johns Hopkins Univ.", 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notebook: "Notes on Lectures to the Advanced Class in Physics, 1879-80," at Johns Hopkins University, 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Diary of Astronomical Observations", 1879-1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Inventory, "Physical Apparatus-S.S.S.", 1883 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Notebook: "Laboratory Observations", 1893-1896 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Lectures on Applied Optics", 1907 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Notes regarding observations of a halo around the sun, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Notes and proofs for New Methods in Geometrical Optics, [1927?] (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "[Colby paper] on certain limitations in Science", undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Notes on Optical Problems", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "On the Influence of Temperature on the Optical Constants of Glass", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "On Lockyer's 'Hypothesis that the So-called Elements are Compound Bodies'", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Laboratory notebooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 19 - 20)
    - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Diary of South American cruise, [pre-1907] (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Certificates of membership in the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America and in the American Philosophical Society, 1889, 1906 (Box 3)